Hi, Larry.
Hi.
I'm Peggy Nathan, National
Council of Jewish Women.
And I want to thank you so
much for your participating
in this tremendously
important project.
It, of course, will be
a permanent oral history
for future generations.
You, I would like to
introduce as Larry Hersh.
And the first thing we'd
like to do is to tell you--
to have you give me a brief
description of yourself today.
All right.
Tell me a little
bit about yourself.
Like you said, my
name is Larry Hersh.
I was born in a small
town called Chust--
C-H-U-S-T-- in
Czechoslovakia, 1925.
I'm 59 years old today.
I lived there till 19--
till I was taken away in 1942.
Well, tell me now, where
do you live now, Larry?
Now, I live in Cleveland
Heights, in the state of Ohio,
under the address of 2573.
I'm married.
I have three
beautiful daughters.
How lovely.
Are you retired?
Not yet.
I see.
But I'm in the
process of retiring.
You're not working
right now, though.
No, I can't work.
Some of it is part of injuries.
I received.
And some of it is
part of injuries
that I brought with
myself from the camps.
I understand.
And you said you're married.
Does your wife work?
No, my wife is an American girl.
And fact of the matter is
she's a Cleveland girl.
She was born here.
And her parents were born here.
And what about-- you said
you have three daughters.
They're all born
here in Cleveland.
One is in college,
going to be a doctor.
How wonderful.
And my second daughter
starts college this year.
And my third daughter
is still in high school.
I see.
OK.
Now, we're going to really
get into your history--
To really the point.
--your history, right.
Can you tell me what your
life was like before the war?
Let's begin with
about 1939 or so.
1939.
You were maybe 24 years
old then, is that correct?
In 1939.
No, in '39, you were--
I'm sorry.
No, in '39 I was--
You were 14.
--14 years old.
You were born in 1925.
'25, yes.
Yes, OK.
I was 14 years old.
I went to school.
And where were you living then?
In Chust, Czechoslovakia then.
It still was.
I see, OK.
This still Czechoslovakia.
Everything was
fine, normal life,
and going to cheder, which
is the Jewish school where
you learn Hebrew and all of the
Jewish rules, laws, and so on.
Sure.
Can you tell me what the
town of Chust was like?
Yes.
There was a population
of about between--
there was about
35,000-40,000 population.
Between them was about between
8,000 and 10,000 Jewish people.
That was a large proportion.
Yes it was a nice Jewish--
Population.
--community.
Yes, a nice Jewish community.
There were about a half a
dozen temples, synagogues--
What big--
--a Hebrew school.
--city were you near?
Munkács, Kosice.
It was somewhere-- it's in
the Carpathian Mountains.
I see.
And it's a section where it
bordered not far with Poland,
from one side, to Romania, from
the other side, and Hungary,
from the other side.
I see.
It was a beautiful,
beautiful country.
Can you tell me about
your family at that time?
We were-- yes.
We were home.
I had my grandparents from both
sides of my parents, uncles
and aunts from both
sides of my parents.
But you all lived together?
In the same-- not-- in the
same area, not together.
But not in the same time--
No, not in the same-- no.
--home.
No, not in the same home, but
in the same area, not too far.
Yeah, I understand.
And also, we had some
relatives here in America.
From my mother's side, we had--
she had two brothers
and two sisters here.
And my father's side, he had
one brother in California.
But I want to know about
your household in Chust.
Am I saying it correctly?
Yeah.
OK.
All right.
You lived with your parents?
I lived with my parents.
And later on--
Did you have
brothers and sisters?
Oh, yes.
I had four sisters.
And we were five kids.
I was the only boy.
And now, I have only one sister.
Three were young.
And they perished
with my parents.
Now, you saw your
grandparents often, though,
because they lived in
the same general area.
Right, right.
How did your family
make a living?
What did your father
do well in those--
just before the war?
My father was a
businessman and happened
to be well-to-do, better than
the most of the Jewish people
around.
He was in the wood business,
in other words, like sample.
Wood?
Wood, yeah, buying
forests and cutting them.
Certainly.
And making-- cutting
into certain lumber.
We would call them
a lumber yard.
Lumber yard and stuff like that.
And he also had a wine cellar--
wine business, which we bought
the grapes and made the wine.
And we were, so to speak--
my father was, so to speak,
an affluent man in town.
You were-- you would
describe yourself
as well-to-do or comfortable?
Well-to-do, right,
comfortable living.
And I always as a kid
had everything I wanted.
And in those days,
especially, sports things,
like having my own
football, skiing, skating,
and all of that,
in those days, it
was a big thing, especially
in the part of the country
where I was--
Sure, skiing, of course.
--and for a kid.
And I had all of those things.
How would you describe
your family's life?
Well, it is an idealistic life
that you can describe only
in the most seldom-seen
way, let's put it this way.
We were all together every meal.
We had-- were together home,
especially the dinners.
And usually, in our time,
the big dinner, the big meal,
was during the dinnertime at--
At noon, you mean?
--at noon, yeah.
And we went to school.
And we used to come home
from school at 1 o'clock.
And by the time 1
o'clock, we used
to sit down and eat,
the entire family.
Then you went-- how nice.
And Saturday and the
holidays, there's
nothing to talk about
it, that is unbelievable.
It's just like a
feast, the family
sitting by the table
every Friday night.
I used to go with
my father to temple,
and come home, and
have a big meal,
and sing, and go with the
religious, so to speak,
ceremonies that goes with it,
and have the kiddush, the wine.
And for Saturday
morning, we used
to all get dressed up fancy,
was the holiday clothes,
so to speak, and go to
Temple again in the morning
and come home, have a big meal.
Religion played a big
part in your life.
Right.
Well, it-- yes, it was not
in the sense of fanaticism
of the religion, but it was
with a sensible religious way.
How about Zionism or other
political organizations?
Was your family interested
or involved in that?
Can you remember
back in those years?
Oh, I do remember well.
I was very much involved.
And my father, he was involved
just by being, so to speak,
supporting one organization or
the other in terms of money.
He did not participate in
too many of those meetings
and all of that.
But therefore, I already
made up for him too.
You were a member
of a Zionist group?
I was a member of the
Zionist organization.
I was the leader of a
Zionist organization,
the whole area of Betar.
This was in your teen years?
Right, of Betar.
And as I grew older,
as we come to it,
we will come to it a
little bit later on,
you will see the
whole operations
and so forth that I was
involved my entire life.
Did socialism or any other
political organizations
play a part in your family life?
Socialism not-- well,
we knew about it.
We talked about it.
But my father could not--
he was considered to be a
bourgeois because the fact
that he was rich and
he was a well-to-do.
So he could not be
a communist already.
Socialism, that was-- we knew
what's going on in Russia.
And we know-- we knew that
the little success they have
with communism.
We know that in the '30s that
the hunger has been going on
in Russia and all of that.
It-- we knew what's going
on in Germany with Hitler.
And we knew what was going on
in the world, far as this goes,
because of radio and as far as
communication was and wasn't.
You were aware of world things.
We were aware worldwide
what's going on.
We knew-- for
example, we even know
what's going on in
America, the Depression.
And we had a little bit of a
firsthand knowledge of that.
In 1933, one of
my uncles-- like I
said, do you remember, I
said, I have a-- my father
had a brother.
His brother came to visit,
came home to Europe.
From America?
Yeah.
And he came home from
America for a visit.
And one day, he got a telegram.
We-- I was a kid.
I don't remember what it was.
But a few days afterwards,
he packed and he left.
Later on, I found out
that he had some--
he was in business.
And he had some kind of
business difficulties.
And he-- they
needed his presence
because of the circumstances.
And he left.
And his mother cried
bitterly that he left.
And that was the end, probably,
that he ever saw his family.
What was the main language
spoken in your home?
In my home-- in the house, the
main language that was spoken
is Yiddish.
We also, all the kids
and the entire family,
everybody in the family, from
my uncles and grandparents, all
the way, we had--
they had at least
three different--
know three different languages.
I, in school, learned already
a little bit of German.
And I knew a little
bit of Hebrew
already-- not in
the sense-- there
was one thing in the prayers,
but the other in the Hebrew.
So it was a different.
So I knew some.
Yeah, the spoken language.
We spoke Hungarian, Czech,
and the local, so to speak,
Russian.
OK.
Were there many
books in your home?
Were you-- was your
family interested in that?
Yes, we had books.
But there was no
library in town.
But there was a different
way of doing things.
For example, if a
new book came out,
I remember reading
Gone with the Wind
in four different languages.
Can you imagine?
Thomas-- what was his name, I
believe, the president's man--
and Steinbeck, I
read those books
in three or four
different languages.
Well, where did you
get these books?
The style was like this.
For example, I had friends.
And we knew there
is a new book out.
So I bought one book.
He bought a different one.
So you would-- you had
your own lending library.
Then we switched around
between ourselves,
and went from hand to
hand, and so on, and so on.
Was there a theater or a
concert hall in the town?
Yes, there was-- no.
A museum of any kind?
No, no museum, nothing
of this nature.
But a concert-- we listened--
we didn't pay too
much attention--
You weren't that.
--to the concert.
But we had a movie house.
And fact of the matter is
we had two movie houses.
And we used to go almost
every night to a movie.
That was the main entertainment.
Were the movies.
Movies.
And then close to the Jewish
holidays, like a Purim,
or in the wintertime,
usually, used to come a--
we used to call them a
troupe, a Jewish group playing
Jewish theater.
And they stayed for
a week or two weeks.
And would entertain.
Right, and then they
used to keep going.
Live entertainment.
Right.
And then used to
go to the next one.
Did your family go on vacations?
Yes, we used to have--
ours was already
considered a big town.
Like I said, we had 35-40, maybe
a few more thousand people.
It was considered to
be already a nice town.
So we used to go
to the countryside
almost every summer, around
July, August, something
like that, for a month.
And to understand how the
Carpathian Mountains is one
of the most beautiful part of--
in any country, which you
could have there mushrooms
and all kind of berries,
and swimming, and fishing,
and mineral waters, and
mineral baths to be taken.
It was just beautiful.
OK.
Now, let's talk about
you, personally.
How do you remember
yourself in those days?
Myself, I remember--
What did you look like?
I looked--
Handsome?
I was a young boy who
loved swimming, loved
playing football, who loved
running, bicycling, loved
to go steal apples from the
neighbor, steal pears and--
An all-around boy.
All-around boy.
Did you have any
special interests other
than the sports?
You mentioned, you
love the sports.
Yes, I played soccer
almost every team--
we had-- every day.
And we had our own team.
And we used to play team against
team, and town against town,
and so on.
It was just everything right.
You have beautiful
memories of your childhood.
Tell you the truth,
that keep me going.
It was everything beautiful.
This is till the-- my age
of 20 when I was still.
I left the age of
17, I should say,
because after this,
it's camp and all that.
It was nothing.
I had everything
my heart desired.
How nice.
I did everything I wanted.
And it's like somebody put
all together a package for me
till the age of
17 that everything
will be put together.
Tell me, what kind of
schools did you attend?
Like I said, I attend cheder.
Then I attended Czech school.
I went to Czech--
But the cheder is just
the religious school?
Right.
Regular, right.
I went to Czech
elementary school.
And then I went-- started--
by the time change came, I
started to go to Hungarian.
And I went to high school,
which was called gymnasium
instead of high school.
I understand.
And till around
the fourth class,
then I had to quit
because Jews were not
permitted to go to school.
That was-- and so how
many years had you
gone to school
altogether in Europe?
Let's see, I had to--
I started out-- my
first year was in 1931.
And I went--
I had altogether about
nine years of schooling.
Did you have any
non-Jewish friends?
Oh, yes, I had many
non-Jewish friends.
And I also had many
non-Jewish enemies,
with which I had to conduct
it very often too many fights.
What do you remember
about antisemitism
in those days of your--
your school days?
In my school days, it had
a peculiar sense to it.
It was a different--
it wasn't in the
sense as antisemitism
as it's known today.
It was more of a, so to
speak, religious bigotry.
In the sense, for an
example, we didn't know--
we could see and
feel when, let's say,
my Gentile friends went
to church Sunday and what
the preacher-- what his sermon
was and if it was anti-Jewish
or--
in the way they acted, in
other words, in the way--
they used to say that good
morning or that good day
or how we used to play football
in the afternoon with the kids.
Or there was times,
for an example,
that they will do
anything for you,
that you would know any--
no boundaries, no difference
whatsoever.
Then another time,
was Jesus killer,
that kind of rotten Jew,
and all that kind of thing.
But I would say, we could
live together like this,
if it had stayed like this,
for another 1,000 years,
and nothing would have happened.
And everything would
have been going smoothly.
And then it gets tough.
You have a fight
there between kids.
Well, childhood.
Right.
Young childhood,
yeah, pranks, and then
Jews playing against
the Gentiles,
and that kind of stuff.
But it had no serious meaning
of any kind of consequence.
Well OK.
Now, we'll get on to--
all right, these
were your teen years.
What do you remember about
the beginning of World War II?
World War II--
When were you first aware
that there was a war?
My beginning of World
War two is started out
in 1938, when Hitler
started in the Sudeten.
We already began to feel
the punch in Czechoslovakia.
The Germans and
the Sudetengebiet,
which was called, starting to
make trouble in Czechoslovakia,
then creating all kind of
confrontations and all of that.
What made you aware that
there were things going on?
Well, we knew what's going
on in the world scene.
We know that Germany
occupied Austria.
And we knew what's going on with
the Jewish people and Hitler's
Germany.
And we knew what's going on
with the Jewish in Vienna
after he moved in in
Austria and so on.
And we knew that nothing
good will come out of it.
Excuse me.
Yeah.
But nobody dreamed that it
will go in such a fast pace
in the way it went and it will
have such a devastating results
as it had.
Were there changes in the way
that non-Jews acted toward you
and your family then?
At that point in
time, we still--
it's-- they are occupying
only the Sudeten part.
We are still Czechoslovakia.
It's-- everybody is restless.
And nobody knows
in what direction.
The fact of-- the
truth of the matter
is that even some of the
Gentiles were afraid.
Because they did not know
what is awaiting, who is what.
And then the major
change came, I remember,
and it was in September--
Of what year?
--of the month of 1939.
No, no that was in
1939 in early spring.
Then it came the change--
What kind of change?
--of a big scale.
Czechoslovakia fall apart.
You mean the government?
Completely.
In other words, Czechoslovakia
as a country fall apart.
The Germans moved in to
Prague, occupied the entire top
of Czechoslovakia.
Poland took a part by Silesia.
The Hungarians took
the rest of it.
And we, in the
Carpathian Mountains,
we became part of Hungary.
We were occupied by Hungary.
I see.
And then the change
was right away.
Well, what changes
did your family
have to make because of that?
First of all that Czech
schools was closed right away.
There was no school.
Everything was changed
from the Czech language
to the Hungarian language.
Well, you were fortunate.
You knew the language.
Yes.
They didn't bother us.
But there were some people who
remembered the Hungarians prior
to Czechoslovakia.
You got to remember
that Czechoslovakia
came into existence after the
World War I. And prior to that,
it was under the
Hungarian Austrian Empire.
So some people remember
the old Tsar and--
I mean the old king, and Franz
Joseph, and all of that era--
my grandfather.
And he had a certain, so to
speak, feeling towards that.
It didn't feel terrible
that this was happening?
No.
It's just change.
Change, right.
And they felt that everything
will in time improve.
And it's just one of
those historical facts.
The Czechoslovakia
disappeared as a country,
as a Czechoslovakia.
And that was that.
But did it-- did that in
itself affect your family?
The family as a
whole, it did not
affect because we
were still all home.
We were all together.
And each one, business as usual.
The fact of the matter
is after a little while,
my father did command his
business with the Hungarians
because they started--
and a year or two later down,
until we were taken away
from home in 1940 and '41,
we have a tremendous business
with them.
Because they bought all
kinds of materials--
raw materials, wood,
fruits, wines, everything.
And they were exporting it to
Germany, to the German Army.
They were already--
And excellent business.
So this business was good.
Of course.
Yes, it was excellent business.
Were you worried
about the future?
Or you thought things
were going to be good?
As time progressed, and as
we existed, in other words,
in our existence, we felt good.
We had everything we needed.
There was nothing missing.
Nobody bothered us
as on a serious way.
We didn't realize
that we have been
living in a fool's paradise.
Because the world
burning around us.
And you know how
human nature is.
Of course.
So we-- if I have
my loaf of bread,
that several hundred
kilometers away from here,
something else is going
on, it didn't bother.
And it was something what's
far away and is happening.
And that's exactly the
way it happened with us.
OK.
Then eventually, the
Nazis entered your town?
No, not yet.
Then in 1942-- '41,
slowly, laws starting
to come out against the Jews.
Right, the Nuremberg laws.
Jews cannot-- these-- that-- the
Nuremberg laws were out already
quite a while.
But they starting to
take effect in Hungary.
I see.
Jews were beaten on the streets.
Well, who-- were there
Nazis there doing this?
They are.
In the meantime, a Nazi
Party was formed already.
And they started to make
all kinds of propaganda.
And in my area, the major
non-Jewish population,
they were not involved.
They were always only the
few who were involved.
And you always will
find a few in everywhere
that they are willing to sell
their soul for-- you know.
Right, right.
And they gave in.
Laws came out.
You couldn't go here.
You couldn't go there.
And the soldier going
around on a rampage,
beating people with a
beard, and beating here.
They found out where a Jewish
family lives, come at night,
and break the
windows, and scream,
holler, make all kind of--
behaving just like
a mob behaves.
And we had to learn
how to contend with it.
And we did.
But your family made their
living in the same way.
Well, the living
started to go down.
Business started to
be badly already.
And in fact, then the business
was taken away and given
to a non-Jew, who--
some of the Hungarians
brought in from deep Hungary,
which we didn't even know
who he is and took away
our businesses.
The only thing what
was left is our house
and that we could stay there.
So then how long
did you stay there?
Your family was
moved eventually.
Eventually, yes, we
were all moved later on.
We came to the ghettos.
All right.
But so things were getting bad.
The business was taken.
Right.
And everything starting
to go downhill.
Right.
Antisemitism became
more a way of life
with the local population,
with the local people.
The young generation,
the young people, friends
with whom I used to play soccer
yesterday didn't know me today.
And it was only one,
maybe two who felt sorry.
But they were afraid
to do anything.
And that was going on not only
in the younger generation,
but also, spilled over
to the older ones.
In other words, for example,
my father knew other fathers.
And he grew up there together.
Yet--
They no longer
spoke to each other.
They did, but it
didn't mean anything.
They-- don't bother me.
I can't do it.
It was--
I see.
Nobody took your part.
Nobody helped you.
Right.
Nobody was-- and in
fact, my grandparents
lived in a village not far from
our hometown, from our town,
from Chust, about 50 or
60 kilometers from there.
And that small village,
there were maybe
30 or 40 Jewish families.
And there was about
500 or more non-Jews.
They started-- and
they grew up there.
They lived all their
life in that village.
Yet they starting already
to feel the pinch.
They wouldn't sell them wood.
And they wouldn't
sell them products.
They would not do this.
And the usual thing, they
used to be everything
without any change.
Nobody was around.
OK.
Looking back, and
you knew-- you saw
what was happening-- do
you recall any plans, then,
that your family made to
deal with this situation?
Or did they feel that
they were helpless?
They was-- let me
give you a sense
to understanding from the
Jewish point of view what
has been going on.
Well, I want to know,
though, about you, yourself,
and your family.
Yeah, it was me and my-- it
was-- involves me my family.
OK, fine.
But in the way things been
going with me and my family
will reflect on the
entire concept of--
Right, and I understand, right.
--existing at that
period of time.
I was a very good student.
And in 1938, in
Czechoslovakia, was
a school in Prague for
special talented youngsters.
I had to go through, I
remember, a special test.
And I came out
with flying colors.
They sent me a
questionnaire to fill out
what I would like to learn,
what sports I would play,
and all of that.
And they wanted
to pay everything.
I had nothing to do,
just to go to the school.
Like a scholarship.
Yeah.
And I wanted-- at
the time, I decided
to be an engineer, engineering.
I wrote back.
They accepted me.
They even sent me home a ticket
and exactly how-- directions
how to go, where to stand, to
arrive, who will wait for me,
and what clothing to bring with
me for sports and football,
and even an instrument, a
musical instrument, to play,
and all of that.
My grandmother from my father's
side, my father's mother,
she went to the rabbi.
And she said to the rabbi, this
and this is going to happen.
My grandson is going
to that kind of school.
The rabbi says, gevalt, he's
going to be eating treyf.
He's not going to be able
to go to temple on Shabbos.
And he's not going to be
able to put on the tefillin.
He's not going to
be able to pray
in the morning and the evening.
He discouraged her.
And that kind of-- she came home
all fired up against my father
and especially
against my mother.
Because my mother was
a very modern woman.
And what are you going?
So my father couldn't bear it.
He had to cancel it.
So in this kind of environment,
in that kind of circumstance,
I'm trying to give
you the concept of.
Now, we teenagers who were
organized in the Zionist
movement, we felt
something is to happen.
But we had no, so to
speak, leadership.
And as you will see
further, you will understand
what I'm talking about.
Because it's hard to
explain how the events went.
We knew something
is about to happen.
We tried to organize the younger
generation already together
as much as possible.
But everything was closed.
We could not move out because
we were framed in, boarded in.
We were already Hungary.
So we could not go
back to Czechoslovakia
because there is
already trouble.
Romanian, all the
borders were closed.
And if anybody was caught,
he was shipped back.
On the other hand was Germany.
Germany was already in Poland.
And Germany was already
in Czechoslovakia.
So what's left?
We couldn't go nowhere.
The only place to go was
Romania or Yugoslavia.
And Yugoslavia, you couldn't
go because Yugoslavia
had their own problems at the
same time as we had in Hungary.
OK.
Let's talk about what happened
to you as the war progressed.
As the war
progressed, and made--
everything went.
In 1942, I was out of school.
I had to leave school.
I couldn't do anything.
Food became a problem, scarce.
Black market started.
Your father wasn't working.
No, he wasn't.
The business was--
Everybody was just staying home.
Oh, yes.
We all staying home.
Everything was taken away.
And you were afraid
to move, almost.
Business didn't
existed-- nonexistent.
A Jew could not do
any kind of work.
He had no job, no businesses.
And then things
starting to go bad.
There was a lot of problems in
the Jewish community because
of the daily needs and
for the daily survival.
So to speak, the well-to-do
Jews had to open their pockets
and do what they
can to help others--
To help others, right.
--more than in the usual way.
And I do remember my father
selling all kind of things
in order not only for us--
to support us or the rest
of the family,
but other people--
To help others.
--others who we knew
and all of that.
OK.
Then they came in.
And were you taken away?
As a family, were you moved?
Then here comes a little
bit of a different--
my life story is a unusual one.
OK.
That's what we want.
And my life story is not
the every survivor story.
That doesn't matter.
We're interested in your story.
My story has a different, as
you will see as I keep going.
All right.
Let's go on.
1943 is approaching.
We had a meeting at the
Zionist organization.
And there was rumors
that for our hometown,
there will be four--
at the time, we
called it certificates
available to go to Palestine.
And this--
Who was issuing these?
They used to be issued from
the British and from Palestine.
And to Hungary used to--
came that Hungary will release--
they will be permitted
to leave, at the time,
if I remember correctly, there
was 150 Jews, young people.
My hometown received
from the 100
the quota of four
to be released.
I understand.
The boys' decision was made that
I will be one of them in going.
I went to Budapest, discussed
with the leadership there.
And they said, yes.
Do you want me to
go for the qualities
that I possess of the
languages I possess that I may
be in a need for a later date?
We don't know what's
going to happen.
And they are predicting--
they feel that I should go.
This was 1942?
That's 1942, close
to the end of 1942.
Or it's late fall, in
the beginning of fall,
let's put it this way.
I came home.
And I said, I'm going
to start packing.
I'm going to leave
for Palestine.
And rumors had it that
there was only four.
And everybody wanted to get out.
My mother-- we sit
down one evening.
And my mother says
to me, are you fair?
I looked at her.
And I says, Mother,
what do you mean?
And she says to me-- these
are the words what she said.
After all, she says--
I used to call me the
macher, my macher.
My mother used to call
me-- here is my macher.
The big man.
Yeah.
So after all, you're
the big macher.
She says, you're the
guy who is running
around all over the place.
And you're the-- why do you--
it will look like you're
taking for yourself.
How about giving it
to somebody else?
After all, you're
a shtetl leader.
So it doesn't look good.
It will look like you
were taking yourself.
So I says, how about if
I give it to my sister,
to my younger sister,
and let her go?
She says, no, you give
it to somebody else.
At the time, I didn't
click, but later on,
the downtime, in--
later on in years,
that she didn't
want us to leave.
We wanted to stick together.
Sure.
Keep the family together.
So anyhow.
But the paradox of it
is the ones who left,
they all survived.
And they are in
Israel till this day.
So I gave it away to somebody
else and the four of them.
And they left for Israel, for
then, at the time, Palestine.
I see.
So then what happened to you?
Then I stayed home.
I had to go around and
make every day problems
to accumulating-- to see for
the everyday daily survival.
Sure.
And my headache was not
only for myself already.
Because there were a lot of
older people who their kids got
stuck all over the world
in different places.
And they could not have
any-- so in other words,
we had to get busy to help
everybody in the way we could.
In '43, things
starting to go worse.
You were still--
We're still home.
--19 years-- 18-19 years old.
You had a lot of responsibility.
Yes.
I still-- responsibilities.
In other words,
I realized, I had
to grow up overnight,
simple fact.
Then we were taken
to the ghettos.
In 1943, we have been
taken to ghettos.
All right.
Now, tell me, the ghettos--
you mean, in your own town?
Let me explain what a ghetto is.
Ghetto is-- of course,
Germans came in already,
occupied the entire section,
the Carpathian link.
And it was under occupation
with the Germans,
but also Hungarians.
The first-- right away, the
first thing what they did is,
in creating the ghetto, is they
going in a section of the town.
Mostly, they looked the sections
where Jews were concentrated.
And they clean out the
all surrounding area,
all of the houses.
If any Gentiles,
they move them out
and they give them
another house,
of a Jewish home or a
Jewish house somewhere else.
Then they bring in all the
Jews from that hometown,
from the whole town, to that
particular designated area.
And they seal it off.
And this is-- we moved in.
We had to move in.
We were five in our family--
I mean, let's see--
there was one boy, four--
we were six in the family.
And so we had one room.
Well, there were four
children-- five children--
Five children.
--and your parents.
My parents.
So there were seven.
Yeah.
Your mother, and father,
and the seven children.
Yes, seven.
Yeah, four girls.
I mean, and the five
children-- four girls and you.
But also, my
grandmother was with us.
So that there were eight.
Eight people.
We had to move in-- eight
of us had to move into a--
to a one room.
In a home.
In a house.
Yeah, it's a house.
But you had one room was
your living quarters.
And we got one room.
And another room was another
family, and a third room
a third family.
I understand.
We were about four or
five families together.
Were these people you knew?
People from-- yes, from--
Jewish people from
your community, right.
--Jewish people
from the community,
from the town, what
we knew very well.
And of course, we
were-- the way it
was conducted is you
come in, say, hey,
you pack tomorrow morning.
You are leaving.
You can take with you
this, take blankets,
get a little bit food to last
you for a couple of days.
You cannot take your jewelry.
You cannot take this, fancy
stuff, coats, and that,
just regular clothing.
And that's the way it happened.
Well, how did you--
what difficulties did
you encounter there?
Who supplied you with
food in the ghetto?
At that time, we are
moving in the-- we are just
moving in in the ghetto.
And we took some food with us.
And by being in the
ghetto, I remember
that we managed to get
a meeting together.
And we decided, we are going
to take the wagons, horse
and buggy wagons.
And we'll go from
house to house.
And whatever food is left
in the Jewish families,
we'll put it in that wagon.
And we'll bring it
in in the ghetto.
And this is--
Oh, you were permitted to go
out during the day to do this?
Yes.
This is still the same
process as is moving out.
We had three, four
days to do that.
In the period of those three,
four days, this is what we did.
So we went out.
And we brought from every house.
We went in in every house.
What we found food,
we put it in--
butter, oil, cheese,
cream cheese, flour,
whatever-- sugar,
whatever we found,
we put everything together.
We brought it in the ghetto.
And then we had
another group who
was dividing it, giving out.
Any family who came and needed
food right away was given.
Right, right, sort
of community living.
Yes.
And--
How long--
--what I didn't
know at the time was
that the Germans
observed who are
top machers who
are doing things,
and who were leading, and so on.
I didn't know that they
already knew who I am,
and what I'm doing,
and they observed me.
After being in the ghetto, and
every settled down a little
bit, quieted down, and
everybody was already--
two days later, one of the
Jewish Judenrat, so to speak,
came in.
And he says, Larry--
my Jewish name was Leibe.
He says, Leibe, this is
the chief of the Gestapo.
And the chief-- there
was a big chief.
He was-- he had a half
a dozen men with him.
He wants to talk to you.
It was fine.
So I came in and
took my hat off.
So he says to me
now, first question
is do you speak German?
So I says, a little bit.
And he says, OK.
He says, I'm going
to test you and see
how little bit you speak.
And he's asking
me some questions,
minor questions-- how
many wagons of food
did you brought in?
And did you got all of it out?
And still-- do you think
there's still some left?
Or can you still get a wagon and
the horses together and get it?
That kind of good approach.
And then he says, how many boys
do you have working with you?
I was naive.
I didn't know what
he is shooting--
Why he's asking this.
--what he is shooting for.
So I gave him all the answers.
And he says, well, your
German is pretty good.
So he says, go ahead and
do what you have to do.
Bring in more food
and all of that.
That lasted for
approximately a good week.
Afterwards, the week
is over, my father
knew another guy, a non-Jew who
was working for the Germans,
was a Hungarian policeman.
But my father used
to give him money,
buy him drinks-- not
years back from before.
So he was standing guard.
They are walking around.
So my father calls him over and
says, hey, he says, be a pal.
Let me cash in a little bit
on you after all those years.
Look, he says, see what you
can find out and let me know.
Says OK.
And one day, he comes
over to my father.
And he says, listen, there
is an order-- the Germans
them self could not come in the
camp to arrest or take anybody.
The ghetto, you mean?
Right.
You had to have the
Hungarians to come in.
He says to me that
listen, there is an order
to take in your son and the
rest of the boys, the names
of another bunch of teenagers,
a whole bunch of young people.
My father heard this.
He got busy.
Till this day, I don't
know how he managed.
But I got-- we used to call it
a [NON-ENGLISH],, which means--
it's a-- from the
army, they call you.
In other words, you have
been recruited to the army--
I understand.
--to the Hungarian Army.
And I had a piece
of paper by saying
that I have been recruited
by the Hungarian Army
to report here, and here, and
here at that and that day--
A call-up
--to call up to duty.
Right, call to duty, right.
Well, if you had this, there
was nobody anything can do.
You just have to go out,
and pack, and leave.
Right.
So that's how you stayed out
of their hands that time.
OK.
Yeah.
But my call was two weeks.
I still had two weeks' time.
Well, was this a
legitimate thing?
A legitimate.
That's everything.
Oh, I thought he
maybe paid somebody.
Oh, yeah, he had to pay it.
But it was legitimate.
Oh, but it was
legitimate, whether you
should go into the army
then go to the Germans.
OK.
Right.
That was legitimate, yes.
But it was bribery.
But it was legitimate.
But it was two weeks later.
I still had two weeks' time.
So in order-- we
tried to figure out
for them what to do
in those two weeks.
Well, rumors got to us that
there are still some papers
available in Budapest.
See, Budapest was
not ghetto yet.
We don't know at the time.
We don't know what's going on.
But we don't--
Papers for what?
For Palestine, you mean?
Not for Palestine, but
to other countries,
to be able to get away.
I see.
That was the time that we
didn't know what's happening.
So since I didn't look Jewish,
I could get away with it.
And not looking like a
Jew, I got dressed up,
and I went to Budapest.
I met with my people
who I knew from before.
And they all said, it's
trouble everywhere.
And they are expecting somebody
to arrive from Palestine
pretty soon, who will
instruct what to do.
And therefore, nothing I can do.
The only thing they
can help me is they
have two pieces of paper.
And they don't know
how much it will work
and how much not
that somebody will
be able to go to
Romania, to escape,
that he will be able to cross
the border and go into Romania.
You preferred--
you didn't really
want to go to the
Hungarian Army.
I'm still home there.
I still have this.
So they didn't know
what to tell me.
They said, we do
the best we can.
Try and stay in touch.
And let's see what happens.
Because we could
not use telephones.
We could have no communications.
It had to-- excuse me.
It had to be on
a personal level.
So nothing accomplishing, I
took those two pieces of paper.
They were like passports,
two pieces of passport.
I came home.
And we had a meeting, who
should be the two to go.
So I wanted one of
them to be my sister.
All the thing we had to do
is to put the picture on it.
And I had a little
piece of rubber
to give it a stamp to make it--
Official.
--have official.
Anything else was-- you know.
So they said, no, we'll
send another couple.
There was a young
couple who just got
married a couple of years ago.
And we decided for them to go.
And we gave it to them.
And they went to Romania.
And they are still
today in Palestine.
They survived.
Time came and I had
to go to the army.
I had to leave.
And here is the saddest
moment of my life.
I kissed my parents
and my sisters goodbye.
I said, I'll be back soon.
And I'll be watching you.
And that's the
last time I ever--
Saw them.
--see them.
So you went into the army then?
I went into the army.
Where did you go?
I went called a city Nagybánya.
How far was that from home?
From home, that was, oh,
about four or five hours' ride
on a train.
And there-- now,
I'm leaving home.
I don't know anything
what's going on home.
I'm different.
No communication.
No communications whatsoever.
No letters, nothing.
I left home.
And I don't know anything
till after the war,
I'm finding out
details from my sister.
I understand.
But till then, I don't know.
But let's talk about--
you went to the army.
Now, how long did
you stay in the army?
Here is a different--
when you say army,
it's a different concept.
You got to understand,
here, with the army,
I happened to have that
we had a colonel who
was a very good guy, who later
became one of those Righteous--
Gentiles.
--Gentiles.
His son is writing a book
right now in Budapest.
And my name will play a part.
What is this man's
name, the colonel?
Gee.
Or his son's name,
do you recall?
He was called Colonel Kelety.
Kelety.
Calady.
Kelety, yeah.
Can you spell it?
K-E-L-E-T-Y.
Oh, OK.
And he's going display.
He's playing a-- he's writing--
his son is putting together
a book.
He was here in America
not too long ago.
And he was there and back.
And I have a special
story with him.
And he dedicated quite
a little bit to that.
How wonderful.
Now, tell me.
So Colonel Kelety was
helpful to the Jewish
To Jewish-- he--
--the Jewish people in the army.
--he was the one who
issued those papers.
But he didn't know that in
between, the between-goers
made money out of that.
Right.
I see.
So in other words,
he was the one
who put the signature on it.
And he is the one who was in--
To call you to the army.
To come in to be under his
regiment, in other words,
under his.
Sure, I understand.
So we came in there.
I reported.
I was taken in,
registered, everything,
issued certain military things--
a blanket and other
few little things.
Uniform, yeah.
No uniform, just on our own--
we went in our own clothes.
Your own clothing, OK.
Yes.
And we just received-- there
was a armband with a stamp in it
from the Hungarian Army.
and this yellow band,
yellow armband, and this
is what we wore.
This tells that you're
a member of the army.
Yes.
Now, as long as
I'm in the armband,
let me go back to the four--
I didn't talk about it.
It was in the ghetto, when
we came in the ghetto,
that everybody had to
wear the yellow star.
And we had to-- should stop?
No, go ahead.
We had the yellow star.
We had to wear the yellow star,
and of course, a strict curfew.
You couldn't go out from--
Sure, the curfew, right.
Right, and all the
restrictions that go with it.
Now, back to the army.
I was been in there for
about four or five days.
We received word that
the local Jewish people
have been taken to the ghettos.
In other words, they
created the same ghetto
that we had in our town
hometown, we created here.
In order to know what's
going on, we right away--
some of the guys there knew me.
And we felt that something
is going to happen,
some different organization
because of the Zionist movement
that I used to be.
I used to organize and all that.
Right away, I organized a
small group of guys who had--
a hard core of guys around me.
Had what?
A hard core of guys.
Hard core.
Oh, to do what?
As we will keep going.
All right.
Well, but we have--
Whatever is going needed,
whatever will be needed to do.
I see.
But you're in the army.
Right.
Yes.
And we are in the army.
All right.
Let's take a little break now.
And we'll come back and
finish this interesting story.
OK.
All right?
All right.